A Guide to the Solicitor General Records of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1764-1794
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Solicitor General Records of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1898-1927
The Library of Virginia
APA 18, APA 19, APA 20, APA 21, APA 22, APA 23
1.8 cu. ft. 5 volumes
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
The position of Solicitor General was created by an act passed by the General Assembly during its session begun in October 1780. The solicitor settled accounts for all debts due the commonwealth, examined the auditor's accounts, and composed lists of taxes raised and the manner of their expenditure. He was authorized to sue for the recovery of delinquent taxes. On 25 November 1791 the General Assembly passed an act terminating the office and the auditor of public accounts assumed its duties on 1 January 1792. Leighton Wood served as Solictor General.
Scope and Content
The Solicitor General records, 1764-1794, include accounts, correspondence, ledgers, letterbooks, returns and settlements.
The records are arranged into 5 series. This collection consists of several Auditor of Public Accounts (APA) accessions that, while identified separately, all pertain to the same category of records. Since the specific APA accession numbers have been used and referenced over the years it was decided that each series would reference it's specific APA number, but one finding aid would describe the entire collection.
Arrangement
Series I: Norfolk Customhouse ledger, 1764-1775 (APA 18)
Series II: Public Debt correspondence and accounts, 1775-1794 (APA 19)
Series III: Peter Penet records, 1781-1782 (APA 20)
Series IV: Letter books, 1781-1791 (APA 21)
Series V: Rough settlements of revenue, 1777-1791 (APA 22)
Series VI: Commissioner of specific taxes returns, 1783-1784 (APA 23)
Contents List
- Series I: Norfolk Customhouse ledger, 1764 Aug 20-1775 Sept 8 (APA 18)., Extent: 1 volume. (Volume 1)
  This volume records the dates of payment of the duties on rum and other alcoholic beverages imported by individuals and companies through the Norfolk Customhouse before the revolutionary war. The ledger also seemed to have been used after the war by the commission appointed to settle the claims of British merchants against American citizens. Later notations in the hand of Leighton Wood, solicitor general, indicate the current residence of the person or company that had paid duties. Indexed.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Ledger, 1764-1775. (Volume 1)
- Series II: Public Debt correspondence and accounts, 1775-1794, undated (APA 19)., Extent: 1.35 cu. ft. (3 boxes) (Box 1-3)
  Public Debt correspondence and accounts, 1780-1792, concerns funds received and expended during the revolutionary war.
  Includes correspondence with the Governor, Council, Board of Auditors, Treasurer, and local officials; and accounts, receipts. Some specific items include: Accounts with Maj. James Quarles (1780); tax on militia / list of balances - Albemarle (1780); lists of justices, magistates, commissioners of tax (specie, specific) and coroners for several counties (1781); account with paymaster of state troops (1781); lists of commissioners (1781); accounts with county lieutenants for recruitment of soldiers (1782); correspondence with John Carter regarding assessments (1782); House of Delegates resolution regarding the Solicitor General and his duties (1782); lists of arrearages due from Commissioners and Commissaries under the provision law and law imposing tax payable on certain commodities (1782); state of taxes that form the revenue of Virginia (1782); letters to the solicitor from Gov. Harrison regarding public debt (1783-1784) correspondence with the Governor and Council (1784); Lists of motions of recruiters and commissioners of revenue on behalf of the Commonwealth (1784); notice to instruct the Attorney General to move for judgment for balance of taxes due from sheriffs (1785); state of claims by foreign creditors, including Beaumarchais and Penet (1785-1793); general state of expenditures (1786); papers of John Webb, Paymaster General of the Navy (1781-1785); General Court - list of motions (1786, 1788); state of taxes from the revenue and memoranda respecting the auditor of public accounts (1786); lists of funds (1786, 1787); correspondence regarding settlement for cash advanced, supplies furnished and services rendered by the state of Virginia to the United States (1786); certification of military service for Larkin Lain (1787); lists of bonds for duties delivered by naval officers (1787, 1788, 1789); correspondence regarding qualifictions, county lieutenants, and duties of the solicitor (1789); list of county lieutenants of the militia and command officers who have been excused for delinquencies (1789); lists of bonds payable for the sale of public vessels (1789); account of the commonwealth with notices (1789); letters regarding public debt (1789); lists of negroes belonging to the estate of John Linton, one of the inspectors at Dumphries Warehous, sold under an execution of the Commonwealth (Commonwealth v. Linton, 1790)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1780. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1781. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of commissioners, 1781. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1782. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of arrearages, 1782. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1783. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1784. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of motions on behalf of the Commonwealth, 1784. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1785. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1786. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Certification of military service for Larkin Lain, 1787. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1787. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of bonds for duties by Naval Officers, 1787. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1788. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of bonds for duties by Naval Officers, 1788. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of motions on behalf of the Commonwealth, 1788. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1789. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and accounts - County lieutenants of the militia, 1789. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Duty bonds, 1789. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of bonds for duties by Naval Officers, 1789. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Notices for motions, 1789. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1790. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1791. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and accounts, undated. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and accounts - Lists of commissioners, undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Foreign creditors, 1785-1788. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Foreign creditors - Beaumarchais, 1780-1793. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Foreign creditors - Papers of Lewis Abraham Pauley re: Peter Penet, 1781-1782. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Foreign creditors - Reshipped foreign goods, 1787-1789. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1782. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1784. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1785. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1786. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1787. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1788. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt, 1790. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters to the solicitor regarding public debt - Governor Benjamin Harrison, 1783-1784. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Papers of John Webb, Paymaster of the Navy, 1781-1785. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series III: Peter Penet records, 1781-1782 (APA 20)., Extent: 18 items (1 folder).
  Peter Penet records, 1781-1782 contain letters to and from Penet regarding his activities as agent, copies of bills of lading and exchange, and correspondence concerning his dismissal and the collection of the debt due the state. Peter Penet served as agent for Virginia in France during the revolutionary war. He was dismissed from the position when a bill of exchange for ten thousand livres was returned for nonpayment. Because the state had already paid this bill, the matter was turned over to the solicitor general for settlement and collection.
  - Records, 1781-1782. (Box 91, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Letter books, 1781-1782, 1784-1791 (APA 21)., Extent: 4 volumes.
  Letter books, 1781-1791, contain copies of letters sent by the solicitor to state and local officials requesting information to assist in settling the state's accounts.
  - Letter book, 1781 Jan 22-1782 Oct 20. (Volume 1)
  - Letter book, 1784 June 14-1786 July 13. (Volume 2)
  - Letter book, 1786 July 13-1788 Oct 31. (Volume 3)
  - Letter book, 1789 Feb 16-1791 Apr 6. (Volume 4)
- Series V: Rough settlements of revenue, 1777-1791 (APA 22)., Extent: 1 folder.
  Rough settlements of revenue, 1777-1791, contain calculations of tax revenues from localities, noting categories of taxes, amounts and dates.
  - Rough settlements of revenue, 1777. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Commissioners of Specific Taxes returns, 1783-1784 (APA 23)., Extent: .25 cu. ft.
  Commissioners of Specific Taxes returns, 1783-1784, include quantity and value of grain collected. During its session begun in 1779, the General Assembly passed an act imposing taxes payable on corn, rye, barley, oats, hemp and tobacco. Commissioners were appointed by local courts to keep acounts of the grain collected and file returns with the auditor of public accounts. Evidently, the returns were then given to the solicitor general to assist in settling the state's accounts. There are no records for Districts 11 and 13. May also include correspondence and lists of insolvents.
  District 1 was comprised of Isle of Wight County, Nansemond County, Norfolk County, Princess Anne County, Southampton County, Surry County and Sussex County. Thomas Newton, Jr., served as the district commissioner. James Holt and Thomas Edmunds served as district recruiting officers. Other names mentioned include William Browne (Surry). (Southampton County and Sussex County became a separate district on April 12, 1783 under James M. Simmons as district commissioner.
  District 2 was comprised of Amelia County, Brunswick County, Chesterfield County, Dinwiddie County, Greensville County, Lunenburg County, Mecklenburg County and Prince George County. Richard Yarbrough served as the district commissioner. (Chesterfield was in District 4 before 1782 May; Lunenburg was in District 4 after 1782 May.) Thomas Edmunds, David Walker and John Stith served as district recruiting officers. Other names mentioned include Daniel Fisher (Greensville) and Lewis Burwell (Mecklenburg).
  District 3 was comprised of Bedford County, Campbell County, Charlotte County, Halifax County, Henry County, and Pittsylvania County. John Talbot served as district commissioner; succeeded by Harry Innes. Hez Morton and Nathan Reid served as district recruiting officers. Thomas Reed (Charlotte) and James Callaway (Campbell) served as county lieutenants.
  District 4 was comprised of Buckingham County, Chesterfield County, Cumberland County, Lunenburg County, Powhatan County, and Prince Edward County. (Chesterfield was in District 2 after May 1782; Lunenburg was in District 2 before May 1782.) John Morton served as district commissioners. Hez Morton, Mr. Kirkpatrick, Ambrose Bohannon and David Miller served as district recruiting officers.
  District 5 was comprised of Albemarle County, Amherst County, Fluvanna County, Goochland County and Louisa County. John Scott served as district commissioner. David Miller, Robert Woodson, Mr. Cowherd served as district recruiting officers.
  District 6 was comprised of Charles City County, Elizabeth City County, James City County, Hanover County, Henrico County, New Kent County, Warwick County, York County and the City of Williamsburg. John Pierce served as district commissioner. John Anderson and Francis Minnis served as district recruiting officers. John Syme (Hanover) and William Clayton (New Kent) served as county lieutenants. Other names mentioned include Nathaniel Wilkerson (Henrico) and Mr. Cowper (Elizabeth City).
  District 7 was comprised of Caroline County, Essex County, Gloucester County, King and Queen County, King William County and Middlesex County. Edward Hill served as district commissioner. Pendleton, Nathaniel Burwell and Francis Minnis served as district recruiting officers. John Peyton served as county lieutenant for Gloucester. Other names mentioned include Anthony Thornton (Caroline), James Pendleton (King and Queen), and John Hickman (King William).
  District 8 was comprised of Culpeper County, Fauquier County, Orange County and Spotsylvania County. Birkett Davenport served as district commissioner. Mr. Cowherd and John Gillison served as district recruiting officers. James Barbour served as county lieutenant for Culpeper.
  District 9 was comprised of Fairfax County, Loudoun County, Prince William County and Stafford County. Richard Graham served as district commissioner. John Gillison, William Johnston and Thomas Mountjoy served as district recruiting officers. Francis Peyton (Loudoun) and Henry Lee (Prince William) served as county lieutenants. Other names mentioned include George Summers (Loudoun), Peter Wagener (Fairfax), and William Garrard (Stafford).
  District 10 was comprised of King George County, Lancaster County, Northumberland County, Richmond County and Westmoreland County. Thomas Jett served as district commissioner. Thomas Brokenbrough, Thomas Parker, John Eustace and Benjamin Grymes served as district recruiting officers. Winder Kenner served as county lieutenant for Northumberland. Other names mentioned include LeRoy Peachy (Richmond).
  District 12 was comprised of Botetourt County, Greenbrier County, Montgomery County and Washington County. Patrick Lockhard served as district commissioner. Thomas Bryan, and Mr. Rhea served as district recruiting officers. Other names mentioned include Samuel Brown (Greenbrier).
  District 14 was comprised of Berkeley County, Frederick County, Hampshire County and Shenandoah County. Joseph Holmes served as district commissioner. James Williams served as district recruiting officer. Other names mentioned include John Smith (Frederick), Philip Pendleton (Berkeley) and Abraham Bird (Shenandoah lieutenant).
  See Journal of the Council of State, v. III, p. 65-66.
  Arranged numerically by district.
  - Returns - District 1, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Returns - District 2, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Returns - District 3, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Returns - District 4, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Returns - District 5, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Returns - District 6, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Returns - District 7, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Returns - District 8, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Returns - District 9, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Returns - District 10, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Returns - District 12, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Returns - District 14, 1783-1784. (Box 1, Folder 12)